New friends. Old enemies.
Wallace & Gromit: Vengeance Most Fowl is a family,
comedy, adventure film directed by Nick Park.
Gromit’s concern that Wallace is becoming too dependent on his inventions proves justified,
when Wallace invents a “smart” gnome that seems to develop a mind of its own.
When it emerges that a vengeful figure from the past might be masterminding things, it falls to Gromit to
battle sinister forces and save his master… or Wallace may never be able to invent again!
Wallace (voice), played by Ben Whitehead.
Chief Inspector Mackintosh (voice), played by Peter Kay.
P.C. Mukherjee (voice), played by Lauren Patel.
Norbot (voice), played by Reece Shearsmith.
Onya Doorstep (voice), played by Diane Morgan.
Judge (voice), played by Adjoa Andoh.
Wallace & Gromit: Vengeance Most Fowl is a 2024 British animated comedy
film produced by Aardman Animations for the BBC and Netflix.
The sixth instalment in the Wallace & Gromit series and the second to be feature-length following The Curse of the
Were-Rabbit (2005), it was directed by Nick Park and Merlin Crossingham and written by Park and Mark Burton.
In the film, Wallace's latest invention is hijacked by a vengeful Feathers
McGraw; it serves as a sequel to The Wrong Trousers (1993).
Ben Whitehead voices Wallace in his first feature-length appearance
following the death of original voice actor Peter Sallis in 2017.
The remaining voice cast consists of Peter Kay,
Lauren Patel, and Reece Shearsmith.
Owing to difficulties with working with DreamWorks Animation during the production of The Curse of the
Were-Rabbit, Park was hesitant on directing another feature-length Wallace & Gromit film for several years.
Vengeance Most Fowl, which was announced in January 2022, with Park and Crossingham attached as directors, and Burton
as screenwriter, was initially conceived as another 30-minute short, before expanding into a feature.
The score was composed by Lorne Balfe and series composer Julian Nott.
Wallace & Gromit: Vengeance Most Fowl premiered at the
American Film Institute on 27 October 2024.
It was broadcast on BBC One and BBC iPlayer on 25 December in the UK and
was released on Netflix internationally on 3 January 2025.
After 28 days of catch-up viewing, it became the BBC's
most watched scripted show since 2002.
The film received critical acclaim, holding a 100% rating on
the review aggregator website Rotten Tomatoes.
It was nominated in the Animated Feature categories at the Academy Awards, Golden
Globe Awards, Annie Awards and the BAFTAs, winning the latter.
It also won the inaugural BAFTA Award for Best Children's & Family Film, in addition
to being nominated for Outstanding British Film at the same ceremony.
The film explores themes of inventor, human animal
relationship, penguin, anthropomorphism, revenge.
The tone is lighthearted.